What has the War on Drugs done to the world?
ما الذي جلبته الحرب على المخدرات للعالم؟
Look at the murder and mayhem in Mexico,
انظروا إلى القتل والتدمير المكسيك
Central America, so many other parts of the planet,
وأمريكا الوسطى والعديد من المناطق الأخرى على الكوكب
the global black market estimated
والسوق السوداء العالمية التي تقدر
at 300 billion dollars a year,
بحوالي 300 مليار دولار سنوياً
prisons packed in the United States and elsewhere,
والسجون ممتلئة في الولايات المتحدة وفي كل مكان
police and military drawn into an unwinnable war
والشرطة والجيش منجرون إلى معركة لا يمكن الفوز بها
that violates basic rights, and ordinary citizens
وتنتهك الحقوق الأساسية والمواطنون العاديون
just hope they don't get caught in the crossfire,
يأملون فقط ألا يحاصروا بين تبادل إطلاق النار
and meanwhile, more people using
وفي الوقت نفسه المزيد من الأشخاص يستخدمون مخدرات
It's my country's history with alcohol prohibition
إنه نفس تاريخ بلادي عند منع المشروبات الكحولية
and Al Capone, times 50.
ووجود مافيات آل كابوني ولكن بـ 50 ضعف
Which is why it's particularly galling to me
ولذلك فإن الأمر مزعج لي كأمريكي
behind this global drug war.
خلف حرب المخدرات العالمية هذه.
Ask why so many countries criminalize
فلتسائل لماذا تجرّم العديد من البلدان
drugs they'd never heard of,
مخدرات لم يسمعوا بها من قبل
why the U.N. drug treaties emphasize
ولماذا معاهدات الأمم المتحدة للمخدرات تؤكد
criminalization over health,
على التجريم أكثر من الصحة
even why most of the money worldwide
ولماذا أكثر الأموال حول العالم
for dealing with drug abuse goes not
المستخدمة لتعالج التعاطي لا تذهب إلى
to helping agencies but those that punish,
مساعدة الوكالات بل إلى تلك التي تعاقب
and you'll find the good old U.S. of A.
ستجد محاسن الولايات المتحدة القديمة
Why did we do this?
لماذا قمنا بذلك؟
Some people, especially in Latin America,
بعض الأشخاص وخاصة في أمريكا اللاتينية
think it's not really about drugs.
يعتقدون أن الأمر لا يتمحور حول المخدرات
It's just a subterfuge for advancing
إنها فقط ذريعة
But by and large, that's not it.
ولكن بشكل عام ليس هذا هو السبب
We don't want gangsters and guerrillas
فنحن لا نريد رجال عصابات ومسلحين
funded with illegal drug money
ممولين بأموال المخدرات االغير شرعية
terrorizing and taking over other nations.
وترهيب والاستيلاء على الشعوب الأخرى
No, the fact is, America really is crazy
لا، إن الحقيق هي أن أمريكا مجنونة حقاً
when it comes to drugs.
حينما يتعلق الأمر بالمخدرات
I mean, don't forget, we're the ones who thought
أعني لا تنسو أننا نحن الذين اعتقدنا
that we could prohibit alcohol.
بإن بإمكاننا منع المشروبات الكحولية
So think about our global drug war
ولذلك فكروا بحرب المخدرات العالمية
not as any sort of rational policy,
ليس كأي نوع من سياسة عقلانية
but as the international projection
بل كالعرض الدولي
of a domestic psychosis.
للهوس المحلي
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But here's the good news.
ولكن إليكم الأخبار الجيدة
Now it's the Russians leading the Drug War and not us.
الآن الروس هم الذين يقودون الحرب على المخدرات لسنا نحن
Most politicians in my country
معظم السياسين في بلادي
want to roll back the Drug War now,
يريدون دحر الحرب على المخدرات الآن
and I'm proud to say as an American
وإنني كأمريكي فخور بأن أقول
that we now lead the world
بأننا الآن نسبق العالم
in reforming marijuana policies.
بإصلاح سياسات الماريجوانا
It's now legal for medical purposes
إنها اليوم شرعية لأسباب طبية
in almost half our 50 states,
في حوالي نصف ولاياتنا الخمسين
millions of people can purchase their marijuana,
ملايين الناس يستطيعون شراء الماريجوانا
their medicine, in government- licensed dispensaries,
دوائهم من مستوصفات مرخصة من قبل الحكومة
and over half my fellow citizens now say it's time
وأكثر من نصف المواطنين يقولون بأنه قد حان الوقت
to legally regulate and tax marijuana
لتنظيم الماريجوانا وترسيمها قانوينا
more or less like alcohol.
مثلها مثل المشروبات الحكولية
That's what Colorado and Washington are doing,
هذا ما تفعله كولورادو و واشنطن
and Uruguay, and others are sure to follow.
والأوروغواي وآخرون سيتبعونهم بالتأكيد
So that's what I do:
فهذا ما أفعله
work to end the Drug War.
العمل لإنهاء الحرب على المخدرات
I think it all started growing up
إعتقد أن الأمر بدأ يتضخم
in a fairly religious, moral family,
في عائلات متدينة وخلوقة
eldest son of a rabbi,
أو أكبر ابن لحاخام ما
going off to university where I
الذهاب للجامعة
smoked some marijuana
حيث دخنت بعض الماريجوانا
and I liked it. (Laughter)
وأحببتها. (ضحك)
And I liked drinking too, but it was obvious
وأحبب المشروبات أيضاً ولكنه كان من الواضح
that alcohol was really the more dangerous of the two,
أن المشروبات الكحولية كانت أكثر الاثنين خطراً
but my friends and I could get busted
ولكنني أنا وصدقائي قد نُضبط
for smoking a joint.
بسبب تدخين سيجارة ماريجوانا
Now, that hypocrisy kept bugging me,
هذا الرياء بقي يزعجني
so I wrote my Ph.D dissertation on international drug control.
ولذلك كتبت أطروحة الدكتوراة عن المكافحة الدولية للمخدرات
I got a security clearance.
وحصلت على تصريح أمني
I interviewed hundreds of DEA and other law enforcement agents
وأجريت مقابلات مع المئات من وكالة مكافحة الإرهاب ووكلاء آخرون مكلفين بتنفيذ القانون
and I'd ask them,
وبدأت بسؤالهم
"What do you think the answer is?"
ماذا تعتقدون كانت إجابتهم؟
Well, in Latin America, they'd say to me,
في أمريكا اللاتينية كانوا يقولون لي
"You can't really cut off the supply.
لا تستطيع أن توقف الإمدادات
The answer lies back in the U.S.,
إن الإجابة موجودة في أمريكا
in cutting off the demand."
في إيقاف الطلب
So then I go back home and I talk to people
ولذلك عدت إلى موطني وتحدثت مع الأشخاص
involved in anti-drug efforts there, and they'd say,
المشاركين بمحاولات مكافحة المخدرات هناك فقالوا لي:
"You know, Ethan, you can't really cut off the demand.
هل تعلم يا إيثان إنك لا تستطيع أن توقف الطلب
The answer lies over there. You've got to cut off the supply."
إن الإجابة تقع هناك. بجب أن توقف الإمدادات
Then I'd go and talk to the guys in customs
ثم ذهبت وتحدثت مع الأشخاص الذين يعملون في الجمارك
trying to stop drugs at the borders,
وحاولت إيقاف المخدرات عند الحدود
and they'd say, "You're not going to stop it here.
فقالوا لي: إنك لن توقفها هنا
The answer lies over there,
إن الإجابة تقع هناك
in cutting off supply and demand."
عند إيقاف الطلب والإمدادات
And it hit me:
وعندها اكتشفت
Everybody involved in this
أن الجميع مشترك
thought the answer lay in that area
بفكرة أن الإجابة تقع في ذلك المكان
about which they knew the least.
الذي يعرفون عنه القليل
So that's when I started reading everything I could
وعند ذلك بدأت قراءة كل شيء
about psychoactive drugs: the history, the science,
عن المخدرات النفسانية وتاريخها وعلمها
the politics, all of it,
سياساتها وكل شيء
and the more one read,
وكلما قرأ المرء أكثر
the more it hit you how a thoughtful,
كلما اكتشف أكثر كم تستطيع
enlightened, intelligent approach took you over here,
طريقة مدروسة ومستنيرة أن تأخذك إلى هنا
whereas the politics and laws of my country
بينما السياسة والقانون في بلادي
were taking you over here.
تأخذاك إلى هنا
And that disparity struck me as this incredible
وفاجئني هذا التباين بكونها
intellectual and moral puzzle.
هذه الأحجية الأخلاقية والفكرية المدهشة
There's probably never been
لعله لم يوجد ما يسمى
a drug-free society.
بالمجتمع الخالي من المخدرات
Virtually every society
كل المجتمعات تقديرياً
has ingested psychoactive substances
قد جربت هذه المواد المخدرة
to deal with pain, increase our energy, socialize,
لتخفيف الألم أو لزيادة الطاقة أو للاندماج في المجتمع
even commune with God.
أو حتى لمناجاة الرب
Our desire to alter our consciousness
إن رغبتنا في التحول عن حالة الوعي
may be as fundamental as our desires
قد تكون مطلباً أساسياً شأنها شأن غيرها
for food, companionship and sex.
كالطعام والصحبة والجنس.
So our true challenge
ولهذا فإن التحدي الحقيقي
is to learn how to live with drugs
يكمن في تعلم كيفية العيش مع المخدرات
so they cause the least possible harm
وهكذا الخروج بأقل خسائر ممكنة
and in some cases the greatest possible benefit.
أو بأكبر قدر ممكن من الفائدة أحيانا
I'll tell you something else I learned,
سأخبركم بشيء آخر تعلمته
that the reason some drugs are legal and others not
بأن السبب وراء تشريع بعض المخدرات وتجريم البعض الآخر
has almost nothing to do with science or health
لا علاقة له بالعلم أو الصحة
or the relative risk of drugs,
أو المخاطر النسبية لتعاطي المخدرات
and almost everything to do with who uses
أوتقريباً أي شيء متعلق بأولئك الذين يستخدمون
and who is perceived to use particular drugs.
أو أولئك الذين وصفت لهم بعض انواع العقاقير المخدرة.
In the late 19th century,
في أواخر القرن التاسع عشر
when most of the drugs that are now illegal were legal,
وكانت معظم المخدرات الممنوعة الآن مشروعة آنذاك
the principal consumers of opiates in my country
القسم الاكبر من مستهلكي العقاقير في بلدي وغيرها
using them to alleviate aches and pains
ممن يستخدمن هذه العقاقير لتخفيف اللآلام والأوجاع
when few other analgesics were available.
عند ندرة المهدئات الاخرى المتوفرة
And nobody thought about criminalizing it back then
ولما يفكر أحدهم وقتها بتجريم تلك العقاقير
because nobody wanted to put Grandma behind bars.
فلم يرد احدهم ان يزج بجدته إلى السجن.
But when hundreds of thousands of Chinese
ولكن عندما مئات الألوف من الصينيين
started showing up in my country,
بدأوا بالتوافد الى بلدي
working hard on the railroads and the mines
حيث عملوا بجد في السكك الحديدية والمناجم
and then kicking back in the evening
وبعدها يتعاطو المخدرات مساءاً
just like they had in the old country
تماماً كما كانوا يفعلون في بلدهم
with a few puffs on that opium pipe,
ببضعة نفخات من غليون الأفيون
that's when you saw the first drug prohibition laws
عندها رأيتم أولى القوانين التي تمنع المخدرات
in California and Nevada,
في ولايتي كاليفورنيا ونيفادا
driven by racist fears of Chinese
تبعاً لمخاوف عرقية من الصينيين
transforming white women
محولة بذلك النساء البيض
into opium-addicted sex slaves.
إلى عبيد جنس مدمنيين على الأفيون.
The first cocaine prohibition laws, similarly prompted
وصدر أيضاً قانون حظرالكوكايين
by racist fears of black men sniffing that white powder
بدافع مخاوف عرقية من السود الذين يشتمون بودرة الكوكايين
and forgetting their proper place
متناسيين مكانهم الملائم لهم
in Southern society.
في المجتمع الجنوبي.
And the first marijuana prohibition laws,
أما القوانين الاولى التي حرمت الماريجوانا
all about fears of Mexican migrants
فكان دافعها مخاوف من المهاجرين المكسيكين
And what was true in my country,
وما كان يجري حقيقة في بلادي
is true in so many others as well,
كان يجري فعلياً في البلدان الأخرى كذلك.
with both the origins of these laws
إن أصول تلك القوانين
and their implementation.
وكذلك تطبيقها
Put it this way,
يمكن اختصارها كالآتي
and I exaggerate only slightly:
وبقليل من المبالغة
If the principal smokers of cocaine
على فرض أن القسم الرئيسي من مدخني الكوكايين
were affluent older white men
يشكلها كبار السن من البيض الأثرياء
and the principal consumers of Viagra
وأن القسم الأكبر من مستهلكي الفياجرا
were poor young black men,
يشكله الشباب من السود الفقراء
then smokable cocaine would be easy to get with a prescription from your doctor
عندها سيكون من السهل الحصول على سجائر الكوكايين بوصفة من طبيبك
and selling Viagra would get you five to 10 years behind bars.
وبيع الفاجيرا سيؤول بك الى السجن ما مدته خمسة الى عشرة سنوات
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now I'm an activist, a human rights activist,
أما الآن فانا ناشط، ناشط لحقوق الانسان،
and what drives me is my shame
يدفعني لذلك شعور بالخزي
at living in an otherwise great nation
من العيش في أمة من المعروف انها عظيمة
that has less than five percent of the world's population
يشكل سكانها ما نسبته أقل من 5% من سكان العالم
but almost 25 percent of the world's incarcerated population.
إلا انهم يشكلون ما نسبته 25% من المسجونين في العالم .
It's the people I meet who have lost someone
والأناس الذين قابلتهم ممن فقدوا شخصاً
they love to drug-related violence or prison
عزيزا في أعمال العنف أو في السجن بسبب المخدرات
or overdose or AIDS
بجرعة زائدة أو بالايدز
because our drug policies emphasize
لأن سياساتنا المتعلقة بالمخدرات تؤكد
criminalization over health.
التجريم أكثر من الصحة
It's good people who have lost their jobs,
والاشخاص الصالحين الذين خسروا وظائفهم
their homes, their freedom, even their children
ومساكنهم وحريتهم وحتى أبناءهم
to the state, not because they hurt anyone
كلها ذهبت للولاية، ليس لانهم سببوا ضررأ لأحد
but solely because they chose to use one drug
بل لانهم ببساطة أختاروا نوعاً من المخدرات
instead of another.
بدلاً من الآخر.
So is legalization the answer?
السؤال الآن: هل تشريع المخدرات هو الحل؟
On that, I'm torn:
وهنا أقف حائراً
three days a week I think yes, three days a week I think no,
ثلاثة أيام أقول "نعم" وثلاثة اخرى أقول "لا"
and on Sundays I'm agnostic.
أيام الاحد أشعر بانني ملحد
But since today is Tuesday,
وبما أن اليوم هو الثلاثاء
let me just say that legally regulating and taxing
اسمحولي أن أقول أن التنظيم القانوني وفرض الضرائب
most of the drugs that are now criminalized
على معظم أصناف المخدرات الممنوعة الآن
would radically reduce the crime, violence,
سيقلل بشكل هائل من الجريمة والعنف
corruption and black markets,
والفساد والأسواق السوداء
and the problems of adulterated and unregulated drugs,
ومشاكل الادوية المغشوشة وغير القانونية
and improve public safety,
وتعزيز السلامة العامة
and allow taxpayer resources to be developed
ويتيح الفرصة لتنمية موارد دافعي الضرائب
to more useful purposes.
لأغراض أكثر فائدة.
I mean, look, the markets in marijuana, cocaine,
وأعني بهذا أسواق الماريجوانا والكوكايين
heroin and methamphetamine
والهيروين والميثامفيتامين
are global commodities markets
كلها تشكل أسواق للسلع العالمية
just like the global markets in alcohol, tobacco,
كتلك الأسواق العالمية المخصصة لتجارة الكحول والسجائر
coffee, sugar, and so many other things.
والقهوة والسكر وغيرها الكثير من السلع.
Where there is a demand,
حيث يوجد الطلب
there will be a supply.
يوجد العرض
Knock out one source and another
أطرق باب أي مصدر وسترى الآخر
inevitably emerges.
قد ظهر حتماً
People tend to think of prohibition
يميل الناس الى اعتبار التحريم
as the ultimate form of regulation
على انه الشكل النهائي للتشريع
with criminals filling the void.
حيث يقوم المجرمون بتعبئة الفراغات.
Which is why putting criminal laws and police
ولهذا السبب فإن وضع القوانين الجنائية والشرطة
front and center in trying to control
في جميع الجهات كمحاولة للسيطرة
a dynamic global commodities market
على سوق السلع العالمية النشط
is a recipe for disaster.
ما هي الا وصفة للدمار.
And what we really need to do
وما نحتاج للقيام به فعلياً
is to bring the underground drug markets
فقط إخراج أسواق المخدرات السرية
as much as possible aboveground
بقدر الإمكان للعلن
and regulate them as intelligently as we can
وتشريعها بصورة ذكية قدر المستطاع
to minimize both the harms of drugs
للتقليل من أضرار المخدرات وكذلك
Now, with marijuana, that obviously means
والآن، مع الماريجوانا، وهذا يعني بوضوح
legally regulating and taxing it like alcohol.
تنظيمها قانونياً وفرض الضرائب عليها شانها شان الكحول.
The benefits of doing so are enormous, the risks minimal.
فوائد القيام بذلك عظيمة والمخاطر ستكون أقل.
Will more people use marijuana?
وهل سيزيد عدد مستهلكي الماريجوانا؟
Maybe, but it's not going to be young people,
هذا محتمل، ولكن لن يكونوا من فئة الشباب،
because it's not going to be legalized for them,
لانها لن تكون مشروعة لهم
and quite frankly, they already have
وبصراحة سيكونون بذلك
the best access to marijuana.
قد حصلوا على مصدر سهل للماريجوانا.
I think it's going to be older people.
أعتقد أنها ستكون مشروعة فقط لكبار السن.
It's going to be people in their 40s and 60s
ستسمح لفئة الاربعينيات والستينيات
and 80s who find they prefer a little marijuana
والثمانينيات الذين يجدون انفسهم يفضلون قليلا من الماريجوانا
to that drink in the evening or the sleeping pill
على ذلك المشروب أو الحبوب المنومة
or that it helps with their arthritis or diabetes
او ما يساعدهم لتخفيف ألم المفاصل او السكري
or maybe helps spice up a long-term marriage. (Laughter)
أو لربما تساعد في إضفاء بعض البهجة إلى حياتهم الزوجية طويلة الامد.
And that just might be a net public health benefit.
او قد تكون لداعي صحي بحت.
As for the other drugs,
اما عن غيرها من الادوية،
look at Portugal, where nobody goes to jail
تمعن في البرتغال حيث لا أحد يذهب للسجن
for possessing drugs,
بمجرد حيازته للمخدرات،
and the government's made a serious commitment
وقد أخذت الحكومة على عاتقها
to treating addiction as a health issue.
التعامل مع الإدمان كقضية متعلقة بالصحة.
Look at Switzerland, Germany, the Netherlands,
انظر إلى سوسيرا وألمانيا وهولندا
Denmark, England, where people who have
والدنمارك وانجلترا حيث تجد الأشخاص
been addicted to heroin for many years
قد أدمنوا على مادة الهيروين ولسنوات عدة
and repeatedly tried to quit and failed
منهم من حاول الاقلاع مرارا ولكن فشلوا في ذلك
can get pharmaceutical heroin and helping services
فبإمكانهم الحصول على هيروين دوائي وخدمات مساعدة
in medical clinics, and the results are in:
في العيادات الطبية، والنتائج ستكون في أن كل من:
Illegal drug abuse and disease
تعاطي المخدرات غير المشروعة والأمراض
health and well-being improve,
وتحسنت الاحوال الصحية والنفسية
taxpayers benefit,
وجامعي الضرائب يستفيدون
and many drug users even put their addictions behind them.
ورمى العديد من مدمني المخدرات الإدمان وراء ظهورههم
Look at New Zealand, which recently enacted a law
أنظر إلى نيوزلندا والتي أصدرت قانوناً
allowing certain recreational drugs to be sold legally
يسمح أن تباع بعض انواع المخدرات الترويحية بشكل قانوني
provided their safety had been established.
بشرط اتخاذ احتياطات السلامة قبل تعاطيها.
Look here in Brazil, and some other countries,
انظر هنا في البرازيل ودول أخرى
where a remarkable psychoactive substance,
حيث نجد مادة مخدرة مميزة
ayahuasca, can be legally bought and consumed
تسمى "الاياهوسكا" والتي يتم شراؤها واستهلاكها بشكل قانوني
provided it's done so within a religious context.
بشرط أن يتم ذلك كله ضمن طقوس دينية.
Look in Bolivia and Peru,
وانظر الى بوليفيا وبيرو
where all sorts of products made from the coca leaf,
حيث يتم انتاج جميع أنواع الاصناف من حشيشة الكوكا
the source of cocaine,
مصدر الكوكايين
are sold legally over the counter
تباع بشكل شرعي في انحاء البلاد
with no apparent harm to people's public health.
بلا ضرر يذكر في الصحة العامة للاشخاص.
I mean, don't forget, Coca-Cola had cocaine in it until 1900,
ناهيك عن الكوكاكولا التي احتوت الكوكايين حتى عام 1990
and so far as we know was no more addictive
حتى الآن فنحن لا نعرف مخدراً أكثر
than Coca-Cola is today.
من الكوكاكولا في وقتنا الحاضر
Conversely, think about cigarettes:
لنقلب الامر الان. فكر بالسجائر:
Nothing can both hook you and kill you like cigarettes.
لا يوجد هناك ما يمكنه توريطك وقتلك كالسجائر
When researchers ask heroin addicts
حين سأل الباحثون مدمني الهيروين
what's the toughest drug to quit, most say cigarettes.
عن المخدرات الذي يصعب تركه بسهولة فكان جواب الغالبية السجائر
Yet in my country and many others,
غير أن الحال في بلدي وغيرها من الدول
half of all the people who were ever addicted
نجد نصف الأخاص الذين عانوا من الادمان في حياتهم
to cigarettes have quit
على السجائر قد تركوها
without anyone being arrested or put in jail
بدون أي اعتقالات أو حبس
or sent to a "treatment program"
أو إرسالك لـ"برنامج علاجي"
by a prosecutor or a judge.
عبر مفتش أو قاضي.
What did it were higher taxes
سبب ذلك كان الضرائب العالية
and time and place restrictions on sale and use
قوانيين تقيد الزمان والمكان وقت البيع والاستهلاك
and effective anti-smoking campaigns.
والحملات الناجحة المناهضة للتدخين
Now, could we reduce smoking even more
والآن، هل بإمكاننا التقليل من التدخين أكثر
by making it totally illegal? Probably.
بجعله محرماً كلياً؟ أمر محتمل.
But just imagine the drug war nightmare
ولكن تخيل فقط كابوس الحرب المخدرات
that would result.
الذي سينتج عن ذلك.
So the challenges we face today
ولهذا فإن التحدي الذي نواجهه الوقت الحاضر
are twofold.
ينطوي على أمرين.
The first is the policy challenge
يكمن الاول في السياسات
of designing and implementing alternatives
تنسيق البدائل وتطبيقها
to ineffective prohibitionist policies,
لسياسات التحريم غير الفعالة
even as we need to get better at regulating
حتى لو احتجنا للتقدم في عملية التشريع
and living with the drugs that are now legal.
والتعايش مع المخدرات المشروعة في الوقت الحاضر.
But the second challenge is tougher,
لكن التحدي الثاني هو الأصعب
because it's about us.
لانه متعلق بنا نحن.
The obstacles to reform lie not just out there
فالعوائق التي تقف في طريق الاصلاح لا تكمن هناك
in the power of the prison industrial complex
في قوة المجمع الصناعي الذي يشبه السجن
or other vested interests that want to keep things
أو المصالح الراسخة التي تريد ابقاء الامور
the way they are,
كما هي
but within each and every one of us.
ولكن داخل كل واحد منا.
It's our fears and our lack of knowledge
انها مخاوفنا وافتقارنا للمعرفة
and imagination that stands in the way of real reform.
وخيالنا الذي يقف في طريق الاصلاح الحقيقي.
And ultimately, I think that boils down to the kids,
وفي النهاية أعتقد ان ذلك سيتسلل لأبنائنا
and to every parent's desire to put our baby in a bubble,
ولرغبة الأهل في حماية أطفالهم
and the fear that somehow drugs will pierce that bubble
وخوفنا من ان تخترق المخدرات هذه الحماية
and put our young ones at risk.
والمخاطرة بحياة الراشدين منهم.
In fact, sometimes it seems like the entire
في الحقيقة يبدو أحيانا أن هذه
War on Drugs gets justified
الحرب على المخدرات تبرر
as one great big child protection act,
على انها أحد الاجراءات العظيمة المتخذة لحماية الطفل
which any young person can tell you it's not.
والتي سيفسرها أي شخص ناضج على انها ليست كذلك.
So here's what I say to teenagers.
وهنا ما ساقوله للمراهقين
First, don't do drugs.
اولاً، لا تتعاطوا المخدرات
Second, don't do drugs.
ثانياً، لا تتعاطوا المخدرات
Third, if you do do drugs,
ثالثاً، إذا تعاطيتموها
there's some things I want you to know,
فهناك أمور أريدكم معرفتها
because my bottom line as your parent is,
لأن ما سأقوله وسيقوله الأهل هو
come home safely at the end of the night
ارجعوا الي بيتك سالماً آخر المساء
and grow up and lead a healthy and good adulthood.
وأنموا وتمتعوا بمرحلة نضج جيدة وصحية
That's my drug education mantra: Safety first.
تعويذتي في التدريس عن المخدرات هي: الامان أولاً
So this is what I've dedicated my life to,
وهذا ما كرست حياتي لاجله
to building an organization and a movement
لبناء منظمة وحركة
of people who believe we need to turn our backs
يشكلها أولئك الذين يؤمنون بالحاجة لتجاهل
on the failed prohibitions of the past
تشريعات الحظر الماضية الفاشلة
and embrace new drug policies grounded in science,
وتبني سياسات جديدة لها اساس من العلم
compassion, health and human rights,
والرأفة والصحة وحقوق الإنسان
and every other spectrum as well,
وغيرها من الاطياف أيضاً
where people who love our drugs,
حيث الاشخاص يحبون مخدراتنا
people who hate drugs,
والاشخاص الذين يكرهونها
and people who don't give a damn about drugs,
والاشخاص الذين لا يلقون بالاً لها
but every one of us believes that this War on Drugs,
ولكن كل واحد منا يؤمن بانها حرب على المخدرات
this backward, heartless, disastrous War on Drugs,
هذه الحرب المتخلفة القاسية المدمرة
has got to end.
لا بد أن تنتهي.
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
تصفيق
Thank you. Thank you.
شكراَ . شكراً
Chris Anderson: Ethan,
كريس أندرسون: إيثان
congrats — quite the reaction.
مبارك- أنظر غلى ردة الفعل
That was a powerful talk.
ذلك كان خطاباَ قوياً
Not quite a complete standing O, though,
وإن لم تكن بتلك الحفاوة البالغة
and I'm guessing that some people here
واتوقع أن بعض الناس هنا
and maybe a few watching online,
وربما بضعة من اولئك المشاهدين
maybe someone knows a teenager or a friend
ممن يعرف مراهقاً أو صديقاً
or whatever who got sick,
أو ممن مرض بسبب المخدرات
maybe died from some drug overdose.
أو لقى حتفه بسبب جرعة زائدة.
I'm sure you've had these people approach you before.
لا بد أنك قابلت أحداً منهم مسبقاً
What do you say to them?
ماذا تقول لهم عادة؟
Ethan Nadelmann: Chris, the most amazing thing that's happened of late
نايدلمان: كريس، من أجمل ما حصل مؤخراً
is that I've met a growing number of people
أنني قابلت عددا متزايداً من الأشخاص
who have actually lost a sibling or a child
ممن فقدوا أخاً أو ابناً
to a drug overdose,
بسبب جرعة زائدة
and 10 years ago, those people just wanted to say,
قبل عشر سنوات ما أراد أولئك الناس قوله
let's line up all the drug dealers and shoot them
لنجمع تجار المخدرات صفاً ونرميهم بالرصاص
and that will solve it.
وذلك سيحل المشكلة.
And what they've come to understand
ولكن ما توصلوا اليه
is that the Drug War did nothing to protect their kids.
ان الحرب على المخدرات لم تقم بشيء لتحمي أبناءهم
If anything, it made it more likely
وإن كان فلقد ضخمت من إحتمال
that those kids were put at risk.
وضع أولئك الأطفال في خطر.
And so they're now becoming part of this
والآن هم يصبحون جزءاً من
drug policy reform movement.
حركة إصلاح للسياسة المتعلقة بالمخدرات.
There's other people who have kids,
هنالك أشخاص لديهم أطفال
one's addicted to alcohol, the other one's addicted to cocaine or heroin,
ممن يدمنون الكحول أوممن يدمنون الكوكايين أو الهيروين
and they ask themselves the question:
وسيسألون انفسهم هذا السؤال:
Why does this kid get to take one step at a time
لما نجد هذا الطفل يتخذ خطوة للامام حيال ذلك
and try to get better
ويحاول أن يتحسن
and that one's got to deal with jail
بينما الآخر يختار السجن
and police and criminals all the time?
والشرطة والمجرمين طوال الوقت؟
So everybody's understanding,
ولهذا فإن الجميع يدركون
the Drug War's not protecting anybody.
بأن الحرب على المخدرات لا تحمي احداً.
CA: Certainly in the U.S., you've got political gridlock
في الولايات المتحدة ترى جموداً سياسياً
on most issues.
حول العديد من القضايا.
Is there any realistic chance of anything
هل هناك فرصة حقيقة لأي شيء
actually shifting on this issue in the next five years?
فعلي يمكنه تغيير الوضع في السنوات الخمس التالية؟
EN: I'd say it's quite remarkable. I'm getting all these calls
ذلك مثير للإنتباه. أتلقى إتصالات
from journalists now who are saying to me,
من صحفيين يقولون لي
"Ethan, it seems like the only two issues
"إيثان، يبدو أن القضيتين الوحيدتين
advancing politically in America right now
اللتان تتقدمان سياسياً في أمريكا حالياً
are marijuana law reform and gay marriage.
هما إصلاح قانون الماريجوانا وزواج المثليين
What are you doing right?"
فما الشيء الذي ستفعله أنت؟
And then you're looking at bipartisanship breaking out
وبعد ذلك تجد نفسك تنظر الى الاحزاب تتفكك
with, actually, Republicans in the Congress
فهناك الجمهوريين في الكونغرس
and state legislatures allowing bills to be enacted
والمجالس التشريعية التي تسمح بسن القوانين
with majority Democratic support,
والحزب الديمقراطي الداعم ذو الاغلبية
so we've gone from being sort of the third rail,
ولذا لم نعد تلك المنطقة المحرمة
the most fearful issue of American politics,
القضية الاكثر إرهابأ في السياسة الأمريكية
to becoming one of the most successful.
لتصبح واحدة من أكثر القضايا نجاحاً
CA: Ethan, thank you so much for coming to TEDGlobal. EN: Chris, thanks so much.
إيثان شكراً جزيلاً لك للمجيء كريس شكراً جزيلاً
CA: Thank you. EN: Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً لك (تصفبق)